Guide to the Leon Lipson Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Leon Lipson papers
1946-1997
MS 2019
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.31
(5 boxes)
The papers consist of research notes, primarily on Soviet law but also including contract, business and international law, and two articles written by Lipson. There are also notes and correspondence relating to the case of Craig Whitney and Hal Piper, two American reporters working in the Soviet Union in the 1970s who were convicted of libeling Soviet television.
Lipson, Leon
Arrangement
The materials are arranged by subject.
Biographical / Historical
Leon Lipson was born in Chelmsford, Massachusetts in 1921. He attended Harvard University, receiving a bachelor's degree in political theory in 1941 and a master's in Soviet languages and literature in 1943. After working at the Foreign Economic Administration, the Department of State and the War Department during World War II, he returned to Harvard Law School, where he was on the Harvard Law Review and received a law degree in 1950. Upon graduation, he worked for the law firm of Cleary, Gottlieb, Friendly and Cox for six years before being recruited for the Yale Law School faculty as an associate professor in 1956. Lipson became a full professor in 1960, William K. Townsend Professor in 1967, and Henry R. Luce Professor in Jurisprudence in 1977, also serving as associate provost of Yale, 1965-1968. After his retirement in 1992, he was appointed Paul C. Tsai Professorial Lecturer in Law at Yale. Professor Lipson specialized in the study of Soviet law and space law. Among his professional writings are Report to the National Aeronautics and Space Administration on the Law of Outer Space " with Nicholas B. Katzenbach, and two publications, Papers on Soviet Law and Law and the Social Sciences, which he edited with Stanton Wheeler. Lipson was married to the former Dorothy Ann Rapoport, with whom he had three children: James Ezra, Abigail, and Michael Aaron. Following the death of his first wife, he married Rita Brackman and gained three stepchildren: Alex, Yvette, and Peter Brackman. Lipson died in New Haven, Connecticut on September 20, 1996.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of research notes, primarily on Soviet law but also including contract, business and international law, and two articles written by Lipson. One unpublished manuscript, "How to Argue in Soviet", with accompanying material, discusses the style and "spirit" of Soviet discourse. The second is a draft and critiques of an article, "Research in the Law of Contracts", a survey of work done primarily by American researchers on contract law from the mid-1930s to 1962. There are also notes and correspondence relating to the case of Craig Whitney and Hal Piper, two American reporters working in the Soviet Union in the 1970s who were convicted of libeling Soviet television. Whitney and Piper were subsequently fined and ordered to print a retraction of articles they had written claiming that the televised confession of a Georgian dissident had been fabricated.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Abigail Lipson, 2015.
Contracts -- United States -- Legal research; Law teachers; Soviet Union. Laws, etc. (Svod zakonov SSSR); Lipson, Leon
- General correspondence and research notes, 1946-1997 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Craig Whitney and Hal Piper case, David Shipler, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- "How to Argue in Soviet"
  - Correspondence, 1960-1969 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Drafts, 1969, undated (Box 2, Folder 2-5)
  - Outline and notes, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Research material, 1927, 1958-1969 (Box 2, Folder 7-13)
  - Transcript of talk, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- "Research in the Law of Contracts," paper for Meyer Institute, draft and critiques, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Research notecards
  - Soviet law (Box 3, Box 5)
  - Contract law (Box 3)
  - Business law (Box 4)
  - International law (Box 4)
  - Notes and drafts (Box 4)